<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>industry | The Data Diary</title>
    <link>https://itsvenu.github.io/tags/industry/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://itsvenu.github.io/tags/industry/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>industry</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://itsvenu.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>industry</title>
      <link>https://itsvenu.github.io/tags/industry/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>JobHunting - Part 2 - Interviews</title>
      <link>https://itsvenu.github.io/post/job-hunt-interviews/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://itsvenu.github.io/post/job-hunt-interviews/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Link to Part-1: &lt;a href=&#34;https://itsvenu.github.io/post/job-hunt-applications/&#34;&gt;JobHunting - Part 1 - Applications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Part-1 of this two part article, I explained about my strategies for finding and applying to jobs as PhD student. In this article, I will explain about my interview experiences. Starting from January 2020, I have been through 20+ interviews, of which only one was in-person interview (In January 2020, Germany didn&amp;rsquo;t have any COVID-19 cases).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing code to solve a problem to explaining my approach to address a scientific question, there were different flavors of interviews. However, many things are common across most of the interviews. Here, I will try to pen down how to increase your chances of making a good impression during interviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-get-to-know-calls&#34;&gt;1. Get to know calls&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are usually the first interactions between you and the company/interviewer, for around 40min to 1hr. In my case, most of the times, the respective department head contacted me for short discussions to let me know what they are seeking and what I have got to offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is your first chance to make a good impression on how your experiences and interests fit to the advertised position. Usually, they will direct the conversation by explaining who they are, overview of the work they are doing and a few additional details about the position. Then, it&amp;rsquo;s your turn to pitch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make a simple story of your education, work experiences, skills you gained through your work and how these skills are useful for the position you are interviewing and briefly about your long term interests. You may repeat this part in several interviews, so spending some time on making it interesting is worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-questions-to-you-from-them&#34;&gt;2. Questions to you from them&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interviewers usually ask you some technical (not very deep) questions to understand your knowledge that is required for the position. These are basically from the work you explained before and relevant areas. You can give them a high-level overview of your technical expertise and add some additional information on what&amp;rsquo;s your critical opinions on current state-of-the-art methodologies. This way you are conveying that you are being careful about the methods you use to address a scientific problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-questions-to-them-from-you&#34;&gt;3. Questions to them from you&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every (good) interviewer will give you a chance to ask some questions. This part of the interview has a great impact on what interviewer thinks of your candidacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always prepared some (read many) questions before the interview that I want them to clarify and discuss. Alongside, I took notes while they were explaining about the work, team and techniques they use regularly in their labs. Do not hesitate to ask as many questions as possible related to the position. Some applicants think asking too many questions is annoying. NO IT&amp;rsquo;S NOT. In fact, every (good) interviewer expects you ask many questions. The more questions you ask, the better impression you leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-talks-and-discussions&#34;&gt;4. Talks and discussions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you made a good first impression and company thinks you &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; for the role, they usually invite you to the company for a full day interview which involves giving a talk on your work, discussion with team members and HR. To my understanding this is what happens in the absence of the pandemic. Due to 2020, some companies did split this part into multiple days and others organized 5-6hr straight zoom interviews. Yes, 5-6hr straight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually, you will receive an agenda with information on who will sit for your talks and with who you will have separate discussions. Research about these members and prepare your talk accordingly. There might be people from very different background and you might want to simplify a few things to reach your content to all members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HR round of interviews are something completely new for people coming from academics. It&amp;rsquo;s not a thing in academic job interview process, at least until the point of PhD, postdoc positions. In one of my initial interviews, I didn&amp;rsquo;t really think of HR round and during the interview I struggled a lot to answer some questions. It&amp;rsquo;s not that they are difficult to answer but you need to storify them beforehand instead of on the spot because these questions involve a bit of hyping yourself. Spend time researching about HR round questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-rejections&#34;&gt;5. Rejections&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You got the interview call. You did a pretty good job with all rounds and very positive. You receive an email that starts with &amp;lsquo;we are sorry to inform you. . .&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s a NO from the company. Though you did your best at every stage of the process, at the end, you only have 50% chance of receiving the offer. Recruiters from companies always prefer experienced individuals (there can be exception where positions are only meant for freshers). If you are competing with someone who has more experience than you (even by marginal amount), your chances might go down, with some exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are someone who achieves everything in the first attempt (do they exist?), great. But if you belong to rest of the cohort, better get comfortable with these kind of rejections to save yourself from emotional toil they cause. At the end of every interview, reflect on your discussion and where you felt difficult to take the conversation forward. Focus on those areas for the next interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to comment/DM (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/itsvenu_&#34;&gt;@itsvenu_&lt;/a&gt;) if you have any questions. Good luck with your transition!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JobHunting - Part 1 - Applications</title>
      <link>https://itsvenu.github.io/post/job-hunt-applications/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://itsvenu.github.io/post/job-hunt-applications/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Link to Part-2: &lt;a href=&#34;https://itsvenu.github.io/post/job-hunt-interviews/&#34;&gt;JobHunting - Part 2 - Interviews&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020 huh!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the unfortunate things going on in the world, most of us had to continue with our careers, work and education. Amongst the few, I have been fortunate enough to defended my PhD in July, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was aiming to move to industry for my next position. I started applying for potential positions of interest way before I completed my thesis. But because of the pandemic, the response rates, interview processes were extremely slow. I have been through almost 20+ interviews (this is not 20+ companies but interviews). Some said NO to me and I said NO to some offers at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I documented my experience of job applications and interviews. Though all this happened in 2020, some of the things we adapted this year might be applicable to following years and my experience might help you in your job hunting process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please keep the following points in mind if something I did is too specific&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was sure to move to industry, so I did not apply for any academic positions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was looking for industry positions where I can do cancer research and publish papers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am a Bioinformatician/Computational Biologist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some points might be personal opinions based on my experience [take it with a grain of salt]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-talk-to-your-supervisor&#34;&gt;1. Talk to your supervisor&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Helping a student with their next career move is part of a supervisor’s job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of your PhD, at least 6 months before your planned thesis submission, discuss your next career move with your supervisor. Ask them if they can connect you with someone who is working in an industry setting. This is the best starting point. If you are lucky and someone has an open position, you can land an interview as soon as possible in this way. However, your supervisor can only influence until that point. Once you are in an interview, it is your job to prove that you are suitable for the position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-exploit-linkedin&#34;&gt;2. Exploit LinkedIn&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a LinkedIn profile but I was never active. It has many useful features and surprisingly a lot more useful for job searching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is what I did, other than making my profile to represent what my experience and skills are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added &amp;lsquo;Open to work&amp;rsquo; tag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Created &amp;lsquo;job alerts&amp;rsquo; with key words (e.g. computational biologist), specific locations and companies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connected to relevant people working in different companies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I received a few (3-4) personal messages from recruiters of different companies that they are looking for someone with similar skills of mine. Though I never proceeded with any of these as my preferences are different than the job requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-regular-checks-on-career-pages-of-companies&#34;&gt;3. Regular checks on career pages of companies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I prepared a list of companies doing research in the field I am interested in and regularly checked their career pages. Though, LinkedIn alerts (created as above) &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; send you notifications if there is a relevant job, it might not alert you if the job is advertised only on the company&amp;rsquo;s website. A safe side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-cold-calling&#34;&gt;4. Cold calling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cold calling is writing to recruiters/PIs about your interest to work with them despite there is no ad for open position from them. Now, this strategy might not work for industry jobs as effectively as in academics for obvious reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote to many people working in the similar roles as I&amp;rsquo;m interested in on LinkedIn. I received very few responses if not none. However, some responses directed me to similar roles in different companies. This will be really useful as you might not cover many companies ad postings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a screenshot of the message I sent on LinkedIn and the response I got&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;P1.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;P1&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;P2.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;P2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-do-not-procrastinate-until-the-deadline-to-apply&#34;&gt;5. Do not procrastinate until the deadline to apply&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Procrastination. We know it&amp;rsquo;s not good. Yet, we all do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever, you come across a job ad you are interested in, do not wait until the last date mentioned in the ad. Apply as quickly as possible to the position. From my personal experience, most (if not all) recruiters do not wait until the application deadline and start responding to applicants. As soon as they receive applications, they start evaluating the candidates and if someone is suitable for the position, they recruit the candidate. You might miss an opportunity by just waiting till the deadline to apply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;6-do-not-wait-for-the-response-from-submitted-application&#34;&gt;6. Do not wait for the response from submitted application&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, many people do not do this but it is worth mentioning. Once the application is submitted, you don&amp;rsquo;t know what happens and there is only 50% chance you will hear from them. Better move on to the next one after finishing an application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;7-keep-a-record-of-all-applications-with-ad-positings&#34;&gt;7. Keep a record of all applications with ad positings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine you applied for a position and you heard from the recruiter after a month. You only remembered applying for the position but not any details about the ad. This might lead to not preparing well for your first round of discussions. As you apply for many positions, it&amp;rsquo;s not possible to remember all the details of each application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For every application, I took the screenshot of the ad and saved it together with CV and cover letter I used for that specific position. This made my life much easier if I was invited for the interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an example organization of one application for which I did several rounds of interviews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;P3.png&#34; alt=&#34;P3&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;8-some-general-advice-for-phd-students&#34;&gt;8. Some general advice for PhD students&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On several occasions, I have seen PhD students asking questions likes, &amp;lsquo;I am still in my final year of PhD, should I start applying or wait until I finish?&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;I haven&amp;rsquo;t completed writing my thesis, should I finish it first and then apply&amp;rsquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you goal is to move to industry, start rolling your applications once you start writing your thesis. You can do both in parallel instead of one after the other. If you land an interview early on, you can gain experience on how the whole process works, even if you fail. If you get an offer, you can request a few months to start your new job. Recruiters will definitely wait if they think you are the right candidate. My first interview was in January 2020, by that time I didn&amp;rsquo;t even finish 20% of my thesis. I always gave an estimate of when will I finish my PhD and everyone was okay with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t loose anything by starting early.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions, please feel free to comment or shoot me a DM on twitter &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/itsvenu_&#34;&gt;@itsvenu_&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck with you applications!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
